<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>grants on Gioele La Manno</title>
    <link>/tags/grants/</link>
    <description>Recent content in grants on Gioele La Manno</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/grants/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>ERC Starting Grant MOVIOLA awarded</title>
      <link>/post/erc_moviola/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/erc_moviola/</guid>
      <description>We are thrilled to announce that the La Manno Lab has been awarded a European Research Council (ERC) Starting Grant for the project &amp;ldquo;MOVIOLA: Cell decision capture and control via joint Raman live and omics profiling.&amp;rdquo;
This 5-year grant (Feb 2026 - Jan 2031, 1.5 million euros) will support our research into understanding the molecular determinants that govern neural cell fate decisions during human brain development.
The MOVIOLA project introduces a novel experimental paradigm that combines live Raman microscopy with multi-modal molecular profiling to capture cells at the precise moments when fate decisions occur.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CZI awards us with a Data Insight grant</title>
      <link>/post/czitools/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/czitools/</guid>
      <description>RNA Velocity is an analysis framework that has become fundamental in the toolbox of the single-cell research community. It allows extracting dynamical information from expression data. After its release, the method was adopted rapidly by the community; however, ways to assess statistical confidence and unambiguously interpret its outputs have not been consolidated. Most noticeably, it is not currently possible to test biological hypotheses by statistical inference on the RNA Velocity estimates.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SNSF Starting Grant awarded</title>
      <link>/post/snsf_starting_grant/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/snsf_starting_grant/</guid>
      <description>We are pleased to announce that the La Manno Lab has received a Swiss National Science Foundation (SNSF) Starting Grant.
This grant will support our research into understanding the role of lipid heterogeneity in brain development. The project combines mass spectrometry imaging with computational analysis to explore how different lipid species contribute to cellular identity and developmental processes in the nervous system.
The SNSF Starting Grant provides essential support for our experimental and computational work at the interface of spatial metabolomics and developmental biology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ERC Starting Grant awarded</title>
      <link>/post/erc_starting_grant/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/erc_starting_grant/</guid>
      <description>We are thrilled to announce that the La Manno Lab has received a European Research Council (ERC) Starting Grant for the project &amp;ldquo;ELATE: Extracting Laws of brain development from single-cell transcriptome dynamics.&amp;rdquo;
This 5-year grant will support our research into understanding the fundamental principles governing brain development through the lens of single-cell genomics and RNA velocity analysis. The project aims to develop new computational methods and apply them to uncover the regulatory logic underlying neuronal differentiation and brain formation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two EPFL life scientists awarded SNSF grants</title>
      <link>/media/ambizione/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/media/ambizione/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The lab has been awarded a SPARK SNF grant!</title>
      <link>/media/spark/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/media/spark/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The lab has been awarded a Human Cell Atlas CZI grant</title>
      <link>/media/czi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/media/czi/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>