<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gioele La Manno on Gioele La Manno</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Gioele La Manno on Gioele La Manno</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Gioele is appointed Tenure Track Assistant Professor</title>
      <link>/media/appointment/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/media/appointment/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>We formulated the lipotype hypothesis</title>
      <link>/post/lipotypehipothesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/lipotypehipothesis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The overall lipid composition of cell membranes is defined by variations in the concentration of hundreds of individual species. Although, in principle, the unconstrained variations of lipid levels are able to generate infinite combinations of lipid composition, the action of regulatory circuits restricts the spectrum of possible lipid configurations in a given cell and under given conditions. Lipid configurations can be seen as a finite number of states that represent local energetic minima of the lipid compositional landscape. Thanks to their interplay with cell signalling, these configurations then promote the establishment of specific transcriptional programmes and of cell phenotypic states. In addition, the stability of lipid configurations allows them to be maintained over time and thus to propagate phenotypic states across cell generations. To reflect their properties of singularity and heritability, we have referred to these lipid configurations as lipotypes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Molecular atlas reveals how brain cells develop</title>
      <link>/media/mousedevpub/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/media/mousedevpub/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Streamlining stem cells to treat macular degeneration</title>
      <link>/media/rpepub/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/media/rpepub/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From cell fat to cell fate</title>
      <link>/post/lipotypes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2022 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/lipotypes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In multicellular organisms, cells are parts of communities in which an individual contributes to the collective phenotype of the community. Appreciating the “social” organization of these cell communities is instrumental to dissecting their physiology and the pathological consequences of their abnormalities. In Capolupo et al. we investigated the lipid metabolism and gene expression of individual human skin cells and found that specific lipid compositions drive cell specialization. Specifically, we found that sphingolipids determine the transcriptional programs of fibroblasts populating in different layers of the human skin. These results reveal an unexpected role for membrane lipids in the establishment of cell identity and tissue architecture&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From cell “fat” to cell fate</title>
      <link>/media/lipotypespub/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/media/lipotypespub/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>“Molecular Tomographer” algorithm maps gene expression in space</title>
      <link>/media/tomographypub/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/media/tomographypub/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two EPFL life scientists awarded SNSF grants</title>
      <link>/media/ambizione/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/media/ambizione/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First preprint of the lab: spatial-omics by tomography!</title>
      <link>/post/tomographybiorxiv/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2020 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/tomographybiorxiv/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We just released the first preprint of the lab, find it &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.08.04.235655v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the summary of what the paper is about:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Genomics techniques are currently being adapted to provide spatially resolved omics profiling. However, the adaptation of each new method typically requires the setup of specific detection strategies or specialized instrumentation. A generic approach to spatially resolve different types of high throughput data is missing. Here, we describe an imaging-free framework to localize high throughput readouts within a tissue by combining compressive sampling and image reconstruction. We implemented this framework to transform a low-input RNA sequencing protocol into an imaging-free spatial transcriptomics technique (STRP-seq) and validated this method with a transcriptome profiling of the murine brain. To verify the broad applicability of STRP-seq, we applied the technique on the brain of the Australian bearded dragon Pogona vitticeps. Our results reveal the molecular anatomy of the telencephalon of this lizard, providing evidence for a marked regionalization of the reptilian pallium and subpallium. Overall, the proposed framework constitutes a new approach that allows upgrading in a generic fashion conventional genomic assays to spatially resolved techniques.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The lab has been awarded a SPARK SNF grant!</title>
      <link>/media/spark/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/media/spark/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Martin and Ana Marija join EPFL as ELISIR fellows</title>
      <link>/media/elisirs2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/media/elisirs2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome Dimitri!</title>
      <link>/post/dimitri_joins/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2019 00:00:00 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/dimitri_joins/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/people/alumni/&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34; &gt;Dimitri Lallement&lt;/a&gt; joins the lab for a Masters thesis project. He is enrolled in the Computer Science Engineering program, ENSIMAG at Grenoble and doing a exchange with EPFL. He has studied his Bachelor at  the University of Bordeaux and studied as Data Scientist Junior at CNES. He wants to face challenging research problem and explore new methods that can help the interpretation of single-cell RNAseq datasets. Welcome Dimitri!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The lab has been awarded a Human Cell Atlas CZI grant</title>
      <link>/media/czi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/media/czi/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Irina Khven</title>
      <link>/people/irinakhven/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/irinakhven/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;short-bio&#34;&gt;Short Bio&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have recently completed my Masters at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.msu.ru/en/info/struct/depts/fbb.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Moscow State University, Department of Bioengineering and Bioinformatics&lt;/a&gt;. During my undergraduate studies I’ve worked in a molecular biology lab and received a comprehensive training in many techniques. Both of my  internships, one in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bc.biol.ethz.ch/research/weis.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Weis lab at ETH Zurich&lt;/a&gt; and another in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://ist.ac.at/en/research/life-sciences/siegert-group/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Seigert lab at IST Austria&lt;/a&gt;, helped me realize that molecular neuroscience is the most exciting branch of modern biology to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose to do my PhD in La Manno group because it is a great chance to work on the interface of neuroscience, developmental biology and systems biology. My project is dedicated to the study of mammalian brain development and spatial omic techniques. Using a set of state-of-art experimental tools like scRNA-seq and &lt;a href=&#34;http://linnarssonlab.org/osmFISH/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;cyclic smFISH&lt;/a&gt;, I hope to be able to contribute to our knowledge in this field.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alex Lederer</title>
      <link>/people/alexlederer/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/alexlederer/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;short-bio&#34;&gt;Short Bio&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a PhD student in the Computational and Quantitative Biology (EDCB) program at EPFL. Originally from the United States, I completed my BSc in Molecular Biology and Computer Science at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pitt.edu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;University of Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt; before working as a research fellow at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.embl.de/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;EMBL Heidelberg&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During my studies, I have been captivated by the concept of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0958166919301430&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;temporal omics&lt;/a&gt; and bioinformatics in light of the big data boom and advances in next-generation sequencing technologies. One ambition of my PhD is to help bridge the gap between experimental and computational approaches, since the most important discoveries in biology will ultimately benefit from a union of these perspectives. I am using single-cell transcriptomic methods to explore the developing nervous system and eye in several species. I am also contributing to expansion of the bioinformatics toolkit available to the single-cell community. I enjoy collaborating as part of an interdisciplinary team and at a university with a strong reputation for working at the interface of biology and computation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proud alumnus of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.embl.de/research/units/genome_biology/steinmetz/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Steinmetz&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biology.pitt.edu/person/karen-arndt&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Arndt labs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
