<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gioele La Manno on Gioele La Manno</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Gioele La Manno on Gioele La Manno</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Christian Schneider</title>
      <link>/people/christianschneider/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/christianschneider/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;short-bio&#34;&gt;Short Bio&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am an MD student visiting EPFL as part of my doctoral research project. While studying medicine at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.charite.de/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Charité&lt;/a&gt;, my research focus has been developing molecular biotechnologies for clinical application in neurological diseases, with projects based in Berlin, India and Central Africa. As part of my home university’s lab for &lt;a href=&#34;https://translationalgenomics.charite.de/forschung/ag_schuelke/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Translational Neurogenomics&lt;/a&gt;, I joined the La Manno Lab with a key interest in quantitative systems biology of single cells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During my research stay at EPFL, I am working on the development of techniques in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.08.04.235655v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;spatial omics&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0958166919301430&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;temporal omics&lt;/a&gt;, both in the wet lab and bioinformatic settings. Currently, I am applying these techniques to study central nervous system development in vertebrates and fruit flies. My long-term vision is to contribute to the convergence of quantitative biology and medical research.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lisa Dravta</title>
      <link>/people/lisadravta/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/lisadravta/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;short-bio&#34;&gt;Short Bio&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have joined the La Manno Lab for a semester project as part of my Master&amp;rsquo;s program in Computational Neurosciences. I will be looking into extracting new information from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.07.02.184051v1.full&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;single cell atlas&lt;/a&gt; of the developmental mouse brain. My background is in Life Sciences and Engineering, with a special focus on neurosciences, genomics, programming and data analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Roger Aylagas Torres</title>
      <link>/people/rogeraylagas/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/rogeraylagas/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;short-bio&#34;&gt;Short Bio&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My name is Roger Aylagas Torres and I am from Barcelona, Catalonia. I studied my BSc in Telecommunication Engineering at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://telecos.upc.edu/en&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Universitat Politècnica de Catalunya&lt;/a&gt; with a minor in Audiovisual Signal Processing and I am currently pursuing a MSc in Advanced Telecommunication also at UPC with the path of Artificial Intelligence for Multimedia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am currently doing my Master Thesis in the La Manno Lab and I am working on building a self-supervised algorithm for the integration of scRNA-seq and scATAC-seq data.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Zahra Moslehi</title>
      <link>/people/zahramoslehi/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/zahramoslehi/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;short-bio&#34;&gt;Short Bio&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I received my B.Sc. degree in Computer Engineering from Yazd University, my M.Sc. degree in Software Engineering from Amirkabir University of Technology, and my Ph.D. degree in Artificial Intelligence from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.iut.ac.ir/en/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Isfahan University of Technology&lt;/a&gt;. During my doctoral studies, I made two research visits at the University of Geneva and University of Sheffield. After my Ph.D., I continued my research and teaching experiences at Isfahan University of Technology, University of Isfahan, and Shahid Beheshti University, Iran.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I joined the La Manno lab as a postdoctoral researcher to develop pipelines for the integration of snRNA-seq and snATAC-seq datasets for clustering purposes and to build robust prediction models of transitions between cellular states. I aim to correlate dynamical changes in the chromatin accessibility landscape with RNA velocity to determine if whether we can build models with which robust prediction of future states can be made. Calculating ATAC-to-RNA distance is not trivial and I will apply machine learning approaches to learn the distance metric function. With my background on metric learning and representation learning, I will work on learning a good distance metric for this integration problem.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ece Asirim</title>
      <link>/people/eceasirim/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/eceasirim/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;short-bio&#34;&gt;Short Bio&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a joint PhD student in the Neuroscience Program (EDNE) between the La Manno and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.epfl.ch/labs/dangelo-lab/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;D&amp;rsquo;Angelo Labs&lt;/a&gt;. I completed my MSc degree in University of Fribourg, working on Drosophila larval &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-020-59614-y&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;circadian rhythms&lt;/a&gt;. My current project focuses on lipidomics and neuroscience, as in the central nervous system, lipids play a crucial role by influencing the firing of neurons and synaptic plasticity. To address the lacking knowledge of lipid metabolism in different brain regions, we aim to build a high-resolution atlas of lipid metabolism in adult mouse brain, both in health and disease conditions. As a group, we thrive to bring a better understanding to questions we are curious about and hope to develop novel approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two EPFL life scientists awarded SNSF grants</title>
      <link>/media/ambizione/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/media/ambizione/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First preprint of the lab: spatial-omics by tomography!</title>
      <link>/post/tomographybiorxiv/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/tomographybiorxiv/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We just released the first preprint of the lab, find it &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.08.04.235655v1&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the summary of what the paper is about:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Genomics techniques are currently being adapted to provide spatially resolved omics profiling. However, the adaptation of each new method typically requires the setup of specific detection strategies or specialized instrumentation. A generic approach to spatially resolve different types of high throughput data is missing. Here, we describe an imaging-free framework to localize high throughput readouts within a tissue by combining compressive sampling and image reconstruction. We implemented this framework to transform a low-input RNA sequencing protocol into an imaging-free spatial transcriptomics technique (STRP-seq) and validated this method with a transcriptome profiling of the murine brain. To verify the broad applicability of STRP-seq, we applied the technique on the brain of the Australian bearded dragon Pogona vitticeps. Our results reveal the molecular anatomy of the telencephalon of this lizard, providing evidence for a marked regionalization of the reptilian pallium and subpallium. Overall, the proposed framework constitutes a new approach that allows upgrading in a generic fashion conventional genomic assays to spatially resolved techniques.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The lab has been awarded a SPARK SNF grant!</title>
      <link>/media/spark/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/media/spark/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Martin and Ana Marija join EPFL as ELISIR fellows</title>
      <link>/media/elisirs2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/media/elisirs2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome Dimitri!</title>
      <link>/post/dimitri_joins/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/dimitri_joins/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/people/alumni/&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34; &gt;Dimitri Lallement&lt;/a&gt; joins the lab for a Masters thesis project. He is enrolled in the Computer Science Engineering program, ENSIMAG at Grenoble and doing a exchange with EPFL. He has studied his Bachelor at  the University of Bordeaux and studied as Data Scientist Junior at CNES. He wants to face challenging research problem and explore new methods that can help the interpretation of single-cell RNAseq datasets. Welcome Dimitri!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The lab has been awarded a Human Cell Atlas CZI grant</title>
      <link>/media/czi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/media/czi/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Irina Khven</title>
      <link>/people/irinakhven/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/irinakhven/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;short-bio&#34;&gt;Short Bio&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have recently completed my Masters at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.msu.ru/en/info/struct/depts/fbb.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Moscow State University, Department of Bioengineering and Bioinformatics&lt;/a&gt;. During my undergraduate studies I’ve worked in a molecular biology lab and received a comprehensive training in many techniques. Both of my  internships, one in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bc.biol.ethz.ch/research/weis.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Weis lab at ETH Zurich&lt;/a&gt; and another in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://ist.ac.at/en/research/life-sciences/siegert-group/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Seigert lab at IST Austria&lt;/a&gt;, helped me realize that molecular neuroscience is the most exciting branch of modern biology to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose to do my PhD in La Manno group because it is a great chance to work on the interface of neuroscience, developmental biology and systems biology. My project is dedicated to the study of mammalian brain development and spatial omic techniques. Using a set of state-of-art experimental tools like scRNA-seq and &lt;a href=&#34;http://linnarssonlab.org/osmFISH/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;cyclic smFISH&lt;/a&gt;, I hope to be able to contribute to our knowledge in this field.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alex Lederer</title>
      <link>/people/alexlederer/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/alexlederer/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;short-bio&#34;&gt;Short Bio&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a PhD student in the Computational and Quantitative Biology (EDCB) program at EPFL. Originally from the United States, I completed my BSc in Molecular Biology and Computer Science at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pitt.edu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;University of Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt; before working as a research fellow at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.embl.de/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;EMBL Heidelberg&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During my studies, I have been captivated by the concept of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0958166919301430&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;temporal omics&lt;/a&gt; and bioinformatics in light of the big data boom and advances in next-generation sequencing technologies. One ambition of my PhD is to help bridge the gap between experimental and computational approaches, since the most important discoveries in biology will ultimately benefit from a union of these perspectives. I am using single-cell transcriptomic methods to explore the developing nervous system and eye in several species. I am also contributing to expansion of the bioinformatics toolkit available to the single-cell community. I enjoy collaborating as part of an interdisciplinary team and at a university with a strong reputation for working at the interface of biology and computation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proud alumnus of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.embl.de/research/units/genome_biology/steinmetz/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Steinmetz&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biology.pitt.edu/person/karen-arndt&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Arndt labs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome Halima!</title>
      <link>/post/halima_joins/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/halima_joins/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/people/alumni/&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34; &gt;Halima Schede&lt;/a&gt; joins the lab for a Masters project. She is enrolled in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.epfl.ch/education/master/programs/lifesciences/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Bioengineering program&lt;/a&gt; and has studied in biology and mathematics at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.mcgill.ca/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;McGill&lt;/a&gt;. With her passion for machine learning and  neural networks and her knowledge of anatomy and genetics she will turn a bunch of omics data in useful insights of the molecular anatomy of the brain. Welcome Halima!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome Anurag!</title>
      <link>/post/anurag_joins/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/anurag_joins/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;/people/alumni/&#34; target=&#34;_self&#34; &gt;Anurag Ranjak&lt;/a&gt; joins the lab for a Masters project. Anurag is a Chemical Engineer with industry experience in software engineering. He will adventure in spatial transcriptpomics and image reconstruction.He recently &amp;ldquo;converted&amp;rdquo; to biology and enrolled in EPFL Masters in Life Sciences. Welcome Anurag!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
