<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gioele La Manno on Gioele La Manno</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Gioele La Manno on Gioele La Manno</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Lada Polyakova</title>
      <link>/people/ladapolyakova/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/ladapolyakova/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;blurb&#34;&gt;Blurb&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a PhD student in the Computational and Quantitative Biology Program (EDCB) at EPFL, working in the La Manno Lab.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Highly Cited Researcher 2025</title>
      <link>/media/highlycited2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/media/highlycited2025/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lipid Brain Atlas preprint released</title>
      <link>/media/lipidbrainatlaspub/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/media/lipidbrainatlaspub/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Lipidomics Architecture of the Mouse Brain</title>
      <link>/publication/lipidbrainatlas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/lipidbrainatlas/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ERC Starting Grant MOVIOLA</title>
      <link>/media/erc_moviola/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/media/erc_moviola/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping the lipid blueprint of life in 4D</title>
      <link>/media/umaiapub/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/media/umaiapub/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Antonio Herrera appointed Group Leader</title>
      <link>/post/toni_group_leader/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/toni_group_leader/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are proud to announce that Dr. Antonio Herrera, a postdoctoral researcher in our lab since 2021, has been awarded a prestigious Ramón y Cajal fellowship!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Toni will start his own research group at the University of Granada, Spain, in the second half of 2026.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During his time in the La Manno Lab, Toni has made fundamental contributions to our research program, including developing computational methods for spatial transcriptomics analysis and contributing to multiple high-impact publications. His work on deep learning methods for imaging and spatial biology has been particularly impactful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are excited to see Toni establish his own independent research program and look forward to future collaborations. Congratulations Toni!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Specialized signaling centers direct cell fate and spatial organization in a limb organoid model</title>
      <link>/publication/limborganoid/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/limborganoid/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unified Mass Imaging Maps the Lipidome of Vertebrate Development</title>
      <link>/publication/umaia/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/umaia/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Congratulations Dr. Irina Khven!</title>
      <link>/post/irina_graduation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/irina_graduation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are delighted to announce that Irina Khven has successfully defended her PhD thesis!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Irina&amp;rsquo;s thesis, &amp;ldquo;Fine-grained mapping of neural progenitors subtypes in the embryonic brain unveils context-dependent roles of signalling on cell fate decisions,&amp;rdquo; represents a major contribution to our understanding of brain development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During her PhD in the EDNE program (2019-2025), Irina made fundamental contributions to mapping neural progenitor diversity using spatial transcriptomics and single-cell approaches. Her work has been instrumental in establishing the lab&amp;rsquo;s spatial transcriptomics capabilities and generating some of the most comprehensive datasets on embryonic brain development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Irina will continue her scientific career as a Postdoctoral researcher at the Institute of Molecular and Clinical Ophthalmology Basel (IOB).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congratulations Dr. Khven, and best wishes for your future research!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spotiflow published in Nature Methods</title>
      <link>/media/spotiflowpub/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/media/spotiflowpub/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spotiflow: accurate and efficient spot detection for fluorescence microscopy with deep stereographic flow regression</title>
      <link>/publication/spotiflow/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/spotiflow/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Midbrain Dopaminergic Neuron Development is Regulated by Two Molecularly Distinct Subtypes of Radial Glia Cells</title>
      <link>/publication/midbraindopaminergic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/midbraindopaminergic/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tissue Reassembly with Generative AI</title>
      <link>/publication/tissuereassembly/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/tissuereassembly/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Congratulations Dr. Halima Hannah Schede!</title>
      <link>/post/halima_graduation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/halima_graduation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are delighted to announce that Halima Hannah Schede has successfully defended her PhD thesis!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Halima joined as a PhD student in 2020 and completed her thesis jointly supervised with Prof. D&amp;rsquo;Angelo. Her research focused on computational approaches for spatialomics data: construction, integration, and analysis of biomolecular atlases. She developed Tomographer and made key contributions to the Lipid Brain Atlas project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Halima has accepted a position as Lead Data Scientist at Implexis Ltd in London. Congratulations and best wishes for your future career!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
