<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gioele La Manno on Gioele La Manno</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Gioele La Manno on Gioele La Manno</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Lab Retreat 2026</title>
      <link>/lablife/lab-retreat-2026/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lablife/lab-retreat-2026/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In January 2026, we did the first La Manno retreat! We spent a night in Le Locle, in the canton on Neuchâtel, and visited the famous Moulins souterrains. We had a lot of science and fun brainstorming sessions, but a highlight was definitely the noodle-cooking session led by our own PhD student Xinyi Huang!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Example Lab Event</title>
      <link>/lablife/example/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lablife/example/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is an example lab life entry. You can add more details here about the event, activity, or moment captured in the photo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To add more lab life entries:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Copy this file and rename it (e.g., &lt;code&gt;lablife/team-retreat-2025.md&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Update the date, title, and summary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add your image to &lt;code&gt;static/img/lablife/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Update &lt;code&gt;image_preview&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;header.image&lt;/code&gt; to point to your image&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write a description in the content area below the &lt;code&gt;+++&lt;/code&gt; markers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each entry will appear as a card in the Lab Life section with the image and short description.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lada Polyakova</title>
      <link>/people/ladapolyakova/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/ladapolyakova/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;blurb&#34;&gt;Blurb&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a PhD student in the Computational and Quantitative Biology Program (EDCB) at EPFL, working in the La Manno Lab.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Highly Cited Researcher 2025</title>
      <link>/media/highlycited2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/media/highlycited2025/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lipid Brain Atlas preprint released</title>
      <link>/media/lipidbrainatlaspub/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/media/lipidbrainatlaspub/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lipid Brain Atlas Released</title>
      <link>/post/lipid_brain_atlas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/lipid_brain_atlas/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;We are excited to announce the release of the &lt;strong&gt;Lipid Brain Atlas&lt;/strong&gt; - a high-resolution mapping of membrane lipids in the mouse brain!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work, led by &lt;a href=&#34;/people/lucafusar/&#34;&gt;Luca Fusar Bassini&lt;/a&gt; in collaboration with Giovanni D&amp;rsquo;Angelo&amp;rsquo;s lab, reveals that &lt;strong&gt;lipids act as zip codes for fine-grained brain anatomy&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;key-discoveries&#34;&gt;Key Discoveries&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lipizones-a-new-way-to-map-the-brain&#34;&gt;Lipizones: A New Way to Map the Brain&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We discovered &lt;strong&gt;lipizones&lt;/strong&gt; - brain territories defined purely by lipid composition, without any anatomical assumptions. Remarkably, lipid profiles alone can predict 3D brain tissue coordinates with high accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;oligodendrocyte-heterogeneity&#34;&gt;Oligodendrocyte Heterogeneity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We found striking lipid heterogeneity among oligodendrocytes in the corpus callosum, suggesting that these cells are far more diverse than previously appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;connecting-cell-bodies-to-axon-terminals&#34;&gt;Connecting Cell Bodies to Axon Terminals&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lipid signatures can connect cell bodies to their distant axon terminals, opening new ways to study brain connectivity through biochemistry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ventricular-system-zonation&#34;&gt;Ventricular System Zonation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We uncovered biochemical zonation patterns in the choroid plexus and ventricular linings, regions critical for cerebrospinal fluid production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pregnancy-and-sex-differences&#34;&gt;Pregnancy and Sex Differences&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps most surprisingly, pregnancy triggers coordinated membrane adaptations across brain regions. We also found sex differences in white matter sphingolipids that amplify during pregnancy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-this-matters&#34;&gt;Why This Matters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The atlas enables tracking how disease, aging, diet, and medications reshape brain lipid composition at the cellular level. This opens new avenues for understanding:
- Cell-type specific metabolism
- Developmental history encoded in membranes
- Connectivity patterns revealed through lipid fingerprints&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;explore-the-atlas&#34;&gt;Explore the Atlas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interactive atlas is available at: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lbae-v2.epfl.ch/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;lbae-v2.epfl.ch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read the full preprint on &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1101/2025.10.13.682018&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;bioRxiv&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Lipidomics Architecture of the Mouse Brain</title>
      <link>/publication/lipidbrainatlas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/lipidbrainatlas/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ERC Starting Grant MOVIOLA</title>
      <link>/media/erc_moviola/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/media/erc_moviola/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping the lipid blueprint of life in 4D</title>
      <link>/media/umaiapub/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/media/umaiapub/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Antonio Herrera appointed Group Leader</title>
      <link>/post/toni_group_leader/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/toni_group_leader/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are proud to announce that Dr. Antonio Herrera, a postdoctoral researcher in our lab since 2021, has been awarded a prestigious Ramón y Cajal fellowship!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Toni will start his own research group at the University of Granada, Spain, in the second half of 2026.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During his time in the La Manno Lab, Toni has made fundamental contributions to our research program, including developing computational methods for spatial transcriptomics analysis and contributing to multiple high-impact publications. His work on deep learning methods for imaging and spatial biology has been particularly impactful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are excited to see Toni establish his own independent research program and look forward to future collaborations. Congratulations Toni!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Specialized signaling centers direct cell fate and spatial organization in a limb organoid model</title>
      <link>/publication/limborganoid/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/limborganoid/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unified Mass Imaging Maps the Lipidome of Vertebrate Development</title>
      <link>/publication/umaia/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/umaia/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Congratulations Dr. Irina Khven!</title>
      <link>/post/irina_graduation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/irina_graduation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are delighted to announce that Irina Khven has successfully defended her PhD thesis!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Irina&amp;rsquo;s thesis, &amp;ldquo;Fine-grained mapping of neural progenitors subtypes in the embryonic brain unveils context-dependent roles of signalling on cell fate decisions,&amp;rdquo; represents a major contribution to our understanding of brain development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During her PhD in the EDNE program (2019-2025), Irina made fundamental contributions to mapping neural progenitor diversity using spatial transcriptomics and single-cell approaches. Her work has been instrumental in establishing the lab&amp;rsquo;s spatial transcriptomics capabilities and generating some of the most comprehensive datasets on embryonic brain development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Irina will continue her scientific career as a Postdoctoral researcher at the Institute of Molecular and Clinical Ophthalmology Basel (IOB).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congratulations Dr. Khven, and best wishes for your future research!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spotiflow published in Nature Methods</title>
      <link>/media/spotiflowpub/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/media/spotiflowpub/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spotiflow: accurate and efficient spot detection for fluorescence microscopy with deep stereographic flow regression</title>
      <link>/publication/spotiflow/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/spotiflow/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
