<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Peoples on Gioele La Manno</title>
    <link>/people/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Peoples on Gioele La Manno</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/people/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Irina Khven</title>
      <link>/people/irinakhven/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/irinakhven/</guid>
      <description>Short Bio I have recently completed my Masters at Moscow State University, Department of Bioengineering and Bioinformatics. During my undergraduate studies I’ve worked in a molecular biology lab and received a comprehensive training in many techniques. Both of my internships, one in the Weis lab at ETH Zurich and another in the Seigert lab at IST Austria, helped me realize that molecular neuroscience is the most exciting branch of modern biology to me.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alex Lederer</title>
      <link>/people/alexlederer/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/alexlederer/</guid>
      <description>Short Bio I am a PhD student in the Computational and Quantitative Biology (EDCB) program at EPFL. Originally from the United States, I completed my BSc in Molecular Biology and Computer Science at the University of Pittsburgh before working as a research fellow at EMBL Heidelberg.
During my studies, I have been captivated by the concept of temporal omics and bioinformatics in light of the big data boom and advances in next-generation sequencing technologies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gioele La Manno</title>
      <link>/people/gioelelamanno/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/gioelelamanno/</guid>
      <description>Bio I earned my PhD at Karolinska Instituet and I am proud alumnus of the Linnarsson Lab. My original training is in Biotechnology (BSc @UNIPA) and Biomedicine (MSc @KI) but nowadays I will probably turn around if somebody is calling out for a Molecular Biologist, Computational Biologist or Bioinformatician.
My research focuses on understanding brain development. I am particularly interested in describing the sequence of states that embryonic stem cells go through during their differentiation towards mature neurons.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Albert Dominguez Mantes</title>
      <link>/people/albertmantes/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/albertmantes/</guid>
      <description>Blurb I am a joint PhD student in the Neuroscience Program (EDNE) between the La Manno and the Weigert Lab. I have a strong interest in the applications of statistical models and data analysis to the health sciences.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alessandro Valente</title>
      <link>/people/alessandrovalente/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/alessandrovalente/</guid>
      <description>Blurb I am a joint PhD student in the Neuroscience Program (EDNE) between the La Manno and D&amp;rsquo;Angelo Labs. I have a strong interest in the applications of statistical models and data analysis to the health sciences. After completing my Bachelor&amp;rsquo;s degree in McGill University, Canada in Biology and Mathematics and my M. Eng in Bioengineering at EPFL, during which I completed an internship in the La Manno Lab, I returned to the lab full time as a PhD student.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alexandre Bouillon</title>
      <link>/people/alexandrebouillon/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/alexandrebouillon/</guid>
      <description>Blurb I am an happy Master student</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Antonio Herrera Camacho</title>
      <link>/people/antonioherrera/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/antonioherrera/</guid>
      <description>Blurb I am an happy postdoc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Daniel Bobrovskij</title>
      <link>/people/daniilbobrovskij/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/daniilbobrovskij/</guid>
      <description>Blurb I am an happy PhD student</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Halima Hannah Schede</title>
      <link>/people/halimaschede/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/halimaschede/</guid>
      <description>Blurb I am a joint PhD student in the Neuroscience Program (EDNE) between the La Manno and D&amp;rsquo;Angelo Labs. I have a strong interest in the applications of statistical models and data analysis to the health sciences. After completing my Bachelor&amp;rsquo;s degree in McGill University, Canada in Biology and Mathematics and my M. Eng in Bioengineering at EPFL, during which I completed an internship in the La Manno Lab, I returned to the lab full time as a PhD student.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Leila Alieh</title>
      <link>/people/leilaalieh/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/leilaalieh/</guid>
      <description>Blurb I am an happy postdoc!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Luca Fusar Bassini</title>
      <link>/people/lucafusar/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/lucafusar/</guid>
      <description>Blurb I am an happy PhD student</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alumni</title>
      <link>/people/alumni/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/alumni/</guid>
      <description>Master Students  img.minion { border: 1px solid #ddd; /*Gray border*/ border-radius: 4px; /*Rounded border*/ padding: 5px; /*Some padding*/ width: 175px; /*Set a small width*/ } /*Add a hover effect (blue shadow)*/ img.minion:hover { box-shadow: 0 0 2px 1px rgba(0, 140, 186, 0.5); } * { box-sizing: border-box; } /*Create two equal columns that floats next to each other*/ .column { float: left; width: 50%; padding: 10px; height: 220px; /*Should be removed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open Positions</title>
      <link>/people/openposition1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/openposition1/</guid>
      <description>Openings and available projects Postdoctoral researcher Read the full call in pdf here!
The research project offered will be focused on the spatio-temporal organization of neural progenitor cells across the developing nervous systems in health and disease. The project, funded by SNF, is low-risk and high-impact.
The overarching goal is understanding the functional implications of the distribution and abundance of radial glial subtypes and the modalities teratogens and metabolic alterations can disrupt it.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>