<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Peoples on Gioele La Manno</title>
    <link>/people/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Peoples on Gioele La Manno</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/people/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Gioele La Manno</title>
      <link>/people/gioelelamanno/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/gioelelamanno/</guid>
      <description>Bio I earned my PhD at Karolinska Instituet and I am proud alumnus of the Linnarsson Lab. My original training is in Biotechnology (BSc @UNIPA) and Biomedicine (MSc @KI) but nowadays I will probably turn around if somebody is calling out for a Molecular Biologist, Computational Biologist or Bioinformatician.
My research focuses on understanding brain development. I am particularly interested in describing the sequence of states that embryonic stem cells go through during their differentiation towards mature neurons.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Halima Schede</title>
      <link>/people/halimaschede/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/halimaschede/</guid>
      <description>Blurb I am a current Masters student at EPFL in the department of Life Sciences and Technology. I completed my BSc in Cell Biology and Anatomy, specializing in genetics, with a minor in Mathematics at McGill University, Canada.
It is here at EPFL where I feel like I have finally found my place in the scientific domain. I have developed a strong interest in machine learning and deep learning algorithms, in particular, their applications to the health sciences.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Anurag Ranjak</title>
      <link>/people/anuragranjak/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/anuragranjak/</guid>
      <description>Biographical notes I am a first year Masters student in Life Sciences in EPFL. I am pursuing a minor in computational neuroscience. Before this i did my Btech &amp;amp; Mtech in Chemical Engineering from IIT Delhi.
I am interested in applying computational methods to solve problems in biology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open Positions</title>
      <link>/people/openposition1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/openposition1/</guid>
      <description>Openings and available projects Postdoctoral researcher We are looking for a talented individual interested in developmental biology, the nervous system and the retina. We particularly welcome applications from experimentalists with experience working with some of the following: mouse embryos, Crispr-Cas9 system, cloning, microscopy, FACS sorting, preparation of sequencing libraries.
PhD student position An interdisciplinary Ph.D. project in developmental neuroscience and systems biology is available at La Manno lab. The successful candidate will use a combination of cutting-edge single-cell genomics techniques, including RNA velocity, to study the embryonic development of the retina.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>