<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Peoples on Gioele La Manno</title>
    <link>/people/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Peoples on Gioele La Manno</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/people/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Lada Polyakova</title>
      <link>/people/ladapolyakova/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/ladapolyakova/</guid>
      <description>Blurb I am a PhD student in the Computational and Quantitative Biology Program (EDCB) at EPFL, working in the La Manno Lab.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evangelia Skoufa</title>
      <link>/people/evangeliaskoufa/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/evangeliaskoufa/</guid>
      <description>Blurb I am the lab technician for the La Manno Lab at EPFL, supporting the team with experimental work and laboratory operations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Laura Lapeña Gil</title>
      <link>/people/lauralapena/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/lauralapena/</guid>
      <description>Blurb I am a PhD student in the Neuroscience Program (EDNE) at EPFL, working in the La Manno Lab.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alireza Gargoorimothlag</title>
      <link>/people/alirezagargoorimothlag/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/alirezagargoorimothlag/</guid>
      <description>Blurb I am a PhD student in the Neuroscience Program (EDNE) at EPFL, working in the La Manno Lab on computational approaches for understanding brain development.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Morgane Storey</title>
      <link>/people/morganestorey/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/morganestorey/</guid>
      <description>Blurb I am a joint PhD student in the Neuroscience Program (EDNE) between the La Manno Lab and Prof. Petersen&amp;rsquo;s lab at EPFL.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Xinyi Huang</title>
      <link>/people/xinyihuang/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/xinyihuang/</guid>
      <description>Blurb I am a PhD student in the Biotechnology and Bioengineering Program (EDBB) at EPFL, working in the La Manno Lab.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Luca Fusar Bassini</title>
      <link>/people/lucafusar/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/lucafusar/</guid>
      <description>Blurb I am an happy PhD student</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alessandro Valente</title>
      <link>/people/alessandrovalente/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/alessandrovalente/</guid>
      <description>Blurb I am a joint PhD student in the Neuroscience Program (EDNE) between the La Manno and D&amp;rsquo;Angelo Labs. I have a strong interest in the applications of statistical models and data analysis to the health sciences. After completing my Bachelor&amp;rsquo;s degree in McGill University, Canada in Biology and Mathematics and my M. Eng in Bioengineering at EPFL, during which I completed an internship in the La Manno Lab, I returned to the lab full time as a PhD student.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rosan Hans</title>
      <link>/people/rosanhans/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/rosanhans/</guid>
      <description>Blurb I am an Industrial PhD student in the Biotechnology and Bioengineering Program (EDBB) at EPFL, working jointly with the La Manno Lab and Roche IHB, supervised by Dr. Giuliana Rossi.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Albert Dominguez Mantes</title>
      <link>/people/albertmantes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/albertmantes/</guid>
      <description>Blurb I am a joint PhD student in the Neuroscience Program (EDNE) between the La Manno and the Weigert Lab. I have a strong interest in the applications of statistical models and data analysis to the health sciences.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Antonio Herrera Camacho</title>
      <link>/people/antonioherrera/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/antonioherrera/</guid>
      <description>Blurb I am an happy postdoc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alumni</title>
      <link>/people/alumni/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/alumni/</guid>
      <description>Master Students  img.minion { border: 1px solid #ddd; /*Gray border*/ border-radius: 4px; /*Rounded border*/ padding: 5px; /*Some padding*/ width: 175px; /*Set a small width*/ } /*Add a hover effect (blue shadow)*/ img.minion:hover { box-shadow: 0 0 2px 1px rgba(0, 140, 186, 0.5); } * { box-sizing: border-box; } /*Create two equal columns that floats next to each other*/ .column { float: left; width: 50%; padding: 10px; height: 220px; /*Should be removed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Master Students</title>
      <link>/people/currentmasters/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/currentmasters/</guid>
      <description> Current Master Students  Francesco Danese - Visiting Student (Italy) Zeineb Mellouli - EPFL Life Sciences Engineering Lothar - Master Student  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open Positions</title>
      <link>/people/openposition1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/openposition1/</guid>
      <description>Openings and available projects Postdoctoral and PhD student positions There are no open positions at the moment. Outstanding candidates might still be considered, to enquires please contact me at gioele.lamanno@epfl.ch.
For Ph.D. students, while direct enquiries are appreciated, to become a Ph.D. student in the lab an official application needs to go through official channels of EPFL-SV doctoral schools: EDNE, EDCB or EDMS. PhD recruitment happens only twice per year, so if interested please keep an eye on the application deadlines.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gioele La Manno</title>
      <link>/people/gioelelamanno/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/gioelelamanno/</guid>
      <description>Bio I earned my PhD at Karolinska Instituet and I am proud alumnus of the Linnarsson Lab. My original training is in Biotechnology (BSc @UNIPA) and Biomedicine (MSc @KI) but nowadays I will probably turn around if somebody is calling out for a Molecular Biologist, Computational Biologist or Bioinformatician.
My research focuses on understanding brain development. I am particularly interested in describing the sequence of states that embryonic stem cells go through during their differentiation towards mature neurons.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>