<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Peoples on Gioele La Manno</title>
    <link>/people/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Peoples on Gioele La Manno</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 18 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/people/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Gioele La Manno</title>
      <link>/people/gioelelamanno/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/gioelelamanno/</guid>
      <description>Bio I earned my PhD at Karolinska Instituet and I am proud alumnus of the Linnarsson Lab. My original training is in Biotechnology (BSc @UNIPA) and Biomedicine (MSc @KI) but nowadays I will probably turn around if somebody is calling out for a Molecular Biologist, Computational Biologist or Bioinformatician.
My research focuses on understanding brain development. I am particularly interested in describing the sequence of states that embryonic stem cells go through during their differentiation towards mature neurons.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Irina Khven</title>
      <link>/people/irinakhven/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/irinakhven/</guid>
      <description>Short Bio I have recently completed my Masters at Moscow State University, Department of Bioengineering and Bioinformatics. During my undergraduate studies I’ve worked in a molecular biology lab and received a comprehensive training in many techniques. Both of my internships - in Weis lab at ETH Zurich and in Seigert lab at IST Austria - helped me realize that molecular neuroscience is the most exciting branch of modern biology to me.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alex Lederer</title>
      <link>/people/alexlederer/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/alexlederer/</guid>
      <description>Short Bio I am an incoming PhD student of the Computational and Quantitative Biology (EDCB) Program at EPFL. Originally from the United States, I completed my BSc in Molecular Biology and Computer Science at the University of Pittsburgh before working as a bioinformatician at EMBL Heidelberg.
During my studies, I have been captivated by the rapidly-growing field of bioinformatics in light of the big data boom and ongoing advances in next-generation sequencing technologies.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Halima Schede</title>
      <link>/people/halimaschede/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/halimaschede/</guid>
      <description>Blurb I am a current Masters student at EPFL in the department of Life Sciences and Technology. I completed my BSc in Cell Biology and Anatomy, specializing in genetics, with a minor in Mathematics at McGill University, Canada.
It is here at EPFL where I feel like I have finally found my place in the scientific domain. I have developed a strong interest in machine learning and deep learning algorithms, in particular, their applications to the health sciences.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Anurag Ranjak</title>
      <link>/people/anuragranjak/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/anuragranjak/</guid>
      <description>Biographical notes I am a first year Masters student in Life Sciences in EPFL. I am pursuing a minor in computational neuroscience. Before this i did my Btech &amp;amp; Mtech in Chemical Engineering from IIT Delhi.
I am interested in applying computational methods to solve problems in biology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dimitri Lallement</title>
      <link>/people/dimitrilallement/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/dimitrilallement/</guid>
      <description>Short Bio Coming Soom</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open Positions</title>
      <link>/people/openposition1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/openposition1/</guid>
      <description>Openings and available projects Postdoctoral researcher Read the full call in pdf here!
The research project offered will be focused on developing new computational approaches to integrate single-cell/nuclei RNA-seq and ATAC-seq data generated from archival material. The successful candidate will develop new analysis approaches and apply them to a comprehensive human oligodendroglia dataset. The overarching goal is understanding gene regulation in the specification and maintenance of oligodendrocyte lineage in the human brain.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>