<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Gioele La Manno</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Gioele La Manno</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>uMAIA published in Nature Methods</title>
      <link>/post/umaia_natmethods/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/umaia_natmethods/</guid>
      <description>We are excited to announce the publication of our work on uMAIA (unified Mass Imaging Analyzer) in Nature Methods.
uMAIA is an analytical framework for the joint analysis of large mass spectrometry imaging datasets. It enables the construction of multidimensional metabolomic atlases by extracting, aligning, and normalizing data into coherent, accurate maps. We applied this framework to study developmental lipidomics, creating detailed 4D lipid maps across embryonic stages.
This work represents a significant step forward in our understanding of how lipid diversity contributes to brain development and cellular identity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spotiflow published in Nature Methods</title>
      <link>/post/spotiflow_natmethods/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/spotiflow_natmethods/</guid>
      <description>We are pleased to announce the publication of Spotiflow in Nature Methods.
Spotiflow is a deep learning method for subpixel-accurate spot detection in fluorescence microscopy images. The method formulates spot detection as a multiscale heatmap and stereographic flow regression problem, achieving state-of-the-art performance on diverse datasets while being robust to different noise conditions.
Key features include: - Subpixel-accurate 2D and 3D spot detection - Optimized for spatial transcriptomics workflows - Robust to low signal-to-noise ratio images - Available as Python library and napari plugin</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>VeloCycle published in Nature Methods</title>
      <link>/post/velocycle_natmethods/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/velocycle_natmethods/</guid>
      <description>We are excited to announce the publication of VeloCycle in Nature Methods.
VeloCycle is a Bayesian model of RNA velocity that couples velocity field and manifold estimation in a unified framework, enabling formal statistical testing of gene expression dynamics. It fits an inferentially coherent model directly on raw data, eliminating heuristics that dominate current scRNA analyses.
Key features include: - Formal statistical testing of dynamics - End-to-end Bayesian inference - Cell cycle speed quantification - Manifold-constrained velocity estimation</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome Luca and Alessandro!</title>
      <link>/post/lucaale_join/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/lucaale_join/</guid>
      <description>Luca Fusar Bassini and Alessandro Valente join the lab for their PhD. Luca is a Biologist with a keen interest in developing computational methods to distill biological insight out of data, Alessandro is Biotechnologist with excellent experience in stem cell engineering and brain organoid models. They are both going to work on the lipidome-transcriptome axis in neurulation. Welcome Luca and Alessandro!.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>We formulated the lipotype hypothesis</title>
      <link>/post/lipotypehipothesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/lipotypehipothesis/</guid>
      <description>The overall lipid composition of cell membranes is defined by variations in the concentration of hundreds of individual species. Although, in principle, the unconstrained variations of lipid levels are able to generate infinite combinations of lipid composition, the action of regulatory circuits restricts the spectrum of possible lipid configurations in a given cell and under given conditions. Lipid configurations can be seen as a finite number of states that represent local energetic minima of the lipid compositional landscape.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>We released the map of cell states in brain development</title>
      <link>/post/devatlas/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/devatlas/</guid>
      <description>Using a combination of sequencing techniques and mathematical methods, our lab has traced the genetic programs that direct the development of each cell in the brain. This molecular map help understanding how the brain develops and provide insights into a range of brain disorders. Nature paper here</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CZI awards us with a Data Insight grant</title>
      <link>/post/czitools/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/czitools/</guid>
      <description>RNA Velocity is an analysis framework that has become fundamental in the toolbox of the single-cell research community. It allows extracting dynamical information from expression data. After its release, the method was adopted rapidly by the community; however, ways to assess statistical confidence and unambiguously interpret its outputs have not been consolidated. Most noticeably, it is not currently possible to test biological hypotheses by statistical inference on the RNA Velocity estimates.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From cell fat to cell fate</title>
      <link>/post/lipotypes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/lipotypes/</guid>
      <description>In multicellular organisms, cells are parts of communities in which an individual contributes to the collective phenotype of the community. Appreciating the “social” organization of these cell communities is instrumental to dissecting their physiology and the pathological consequences of their abnormalities. In Capolupo et al. we investigated the lipid metabolism and gene expression of individual human skin cells and found that specific lipid compositions drive cell specialization. Specifically, we found that sphingolipids determine the transcriptional programs of fibroblasts populating in different layers of the human skin.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SNSF Starting Grant awarded</title>
      <link>/post/snsf_starting_grant/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/snsf_starting_grant/</guid>
      <description>We are pleased to announce that the La Manno Lab has received a Swiss National Science Foundation (SNSF) Starting Grant.
This grant will support our research into understanding the role of lipid heterogeneity in brain development. The project combines mass spectrometry imaging with computational analysis to explore how different lipid species contribute to cellular identity and developmental processes in the nervous system.
The SNSF Starting Grant provides essential support for our experimental and computational work at the interface of spatial metabolomics and developmental biology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ERC Starting Grant awarded</title>
      <link>/post/erc_starting_grant/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/erc_starting_grant/</guid>
      <description>We are thrilled to announce that the La Manno Lab has received a European Research Council (ERC) Starting Grant for the project &amp;ldquo;ELATE: Extracting Laws of brain development from single-cell transcriptome dynamics.&amp;rdquo;
This 5-year grant will support our research into understanding the fundamental principles governing brain development through the lens of single-cell genomics and RNA velocity analysis. The project aims to develop new computational methods and apply them to uncover the regulatory logic underlying neuronal differentiation and brain formation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First preprint of the lab: spatial-omics by tomography!</title>
      <link>/post/tomographybiorxiv/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/tomographybiorxiv/</guid>
      <description>We just released the first preprint of the lab, find it here.
This is the summary of what the paper is about:
Genomics techniques are currently being adapted to provide spatially resolved omics profiling. However, the adaptation of each new method typically requires the setup of specific detection strategies or specialized instrumentation. A generic approach to spatially resolve different types of high throughput data is missing. Here, we describe an imaging-free framework to localize high throughput readouts within a tissue by combining compressive sampling and image reconstruction.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome Dimitri!</title>
      <link>/post/dimitri_joins/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/dimitri_joins/</guid>
      <description>Dimitri Lallement joins the lab for a Masters thesis project. He is enrolled in the Computer Science Engineering program, ENSIMAG at Grenoble and doing a exchange with EPFL. He has studied his Bachelor at the University of Bordeaux and studied as Data Scientist Junior at CNES. He wants to face challenging research problem and explore new methods that can help the interpretation of single-cell RNAseq datasets. Welcome Dimitri!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome Halima!</title>
      <link>/post/halima_joins/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/halima_joins/</guid>
      <description>Halima Schede joins the lab for a Masters project. She is enrolled in the Bioengineering program and has studied in biology and mathematics at McGill. With her passion for machine learning and neural networks and her knowledge of anatomy and genetics she will turn a bunch of omics data in useful insights of the molecular anatomy of the brain. Welcome Halima!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome Anurag!</title>
      <link>/post/anurag_joins/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/anurag_joins/</guid>
      <description>Anurag Ranjak joins the lab for a Masters project. Anurag is a Chemical Engineer with industry experience in software engineering. He will adventure in spatial transcriptpomics and image reconstruction.He recently &amp;ldquo;converted&amp;rdquo; to biology and enrolled in EPFL Masters in Life Sciences. Welcome Anurag!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RNA velocity is out in Nature</title>
      <link>/post/velocitynature/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/velocitynature/</guid>
      <description>In a previous preprint RNA velocity in single cells we had presented the discovery that standard RNA-seq data contains additional information on the rate and direction of change in gene expression. If you haven&amp;rsquo;t read what this is about you can see my previous post or directly go and read the more eloquent Nature News and Views kindly written by Allon Klein.
Now our work has gone through the process of peer review.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visiting EPFL and super-postdocs in Europe</title>
      <link>/post/elifrcandidate/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/elifrcandidate/</guid>
      <description>Over the last few days I have been at the École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne (EPFL), Switzerland. The reason of this little trip is that the School of Life Sciences at EPFL recently opened a special position, the fellowship goes under the long name &amp;ldquo;EPFL Life Sciences Early Independence Research Scholar&amp;rdquo; shortened &amp;ldquo;ELIFR fellow&amp;rdquo;.
To explain what an ELIFR fellow is I could simply refer to it as a &amp;ldquo;super-postdoc&amp;rdquo;, a funny term popularized by this commentary on Cell but maybe, not yet so popular in Europe (so that I noticed that using it in a conversation often produces raised eyebrows and a grin or two).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>osmFISH is really awesome</title>
      <link>/post/osmfish/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/osmfish/</guid>
      <description>Simone Codelluppi and Lars Borm have developed and optimized a cyclic smFISH protocol, termed ouroboros smFISH, to quantify the expression of a large number of genes in tissue sections. The goal was building a cell type map of the mouse somatosensory cortex. The results are really impressive. See the fantastic images and interactively explore the data using the Loom viewer here.
Great news are not only is taht Lars and Simore have put a lot of effort to make it possible for any lab to set up the method and they provide detailed protocol and a polished software package.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RNA velocity preprint</title>
      <link>/post/velocity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/velocity/</guid>
      <description>Single-cell RNA-seq measurements provide a powerful approach for studying complex biological tissues. Some of the more interesting contexts involve dynamic processes, such as development or disease progression. However single-cell measurements only capture a snapshot of a transcriptional state at a single point in time.
Several approaches have been developed to infer dynamic processes, such as branching lineages from this scRNA-seq. Usually those methods require many strong assumptions that are often violated.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>