<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Gioele La Manno</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Gioele La Manno</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Antonio Herrera appointed Group Leader</title>
      <link>/post/toni_group_leader/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/toni_group_leader/</guid>
      <description>We are proud to announce that Dr. Antonio Herrera, a postdoctoral researcher in our lab since 2021, has been awarded a prestigious Ramón y Cajal fellowship!
Toni will start his own research group at the University of Granada, Spain, in the second half of 2026.
During his time in the La Manno Lab, Toni has made fundamental contributions to our research program, including developing computational methods for spatial transcriptomics analysis and contributing to multiple high-impact publications.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Congratulations Dr. Irina Khven!</title>
      <link>/post/irina_graduation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/irina_graduation/</guid>
      <description>We are delighted to announce that Irina Khven has successfully defended her PhD thesis!
Irina&amp;rsquo;s thesis, &amp;ldquo;Fine-grained mapping of neural progenitors subtypes in the embryonic brain unveils context-dependent roles of signalling on cell fate decisions,&amp;rdquo; represents a major contribution to our understanding of brain development.
During her PhD in the EDNE program (2019-2025), Irina made fundamental contributions to mapping neural progenitor diversity using spatial transcriptomics and single-cell approaches. Her work has been instrumental in establishing the lab&amp;rsquo;s spatial transcriptomics capabilities and generating some of the most comprehensive datasets on embryonic brain development.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome Laura, Evangelia, and Lada!</title>
      <link>/post/2025_cohort_joins/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2025_cohort_joins/</guid>
      <description>We are thrilled to welcome three new members to the La Manno Lab!
Laura Lapeña Gil joins us as a PhD student in the Neuroscience Program (EDNE) to work on brain development research.
Evangelia Skoufa joins as our lab technician, supporting the team with experimental work and laboratory operations including spatial transcriptomics.
Lada Polyakova joins as a PhD student in the Computational and Quantitative Biology Program (EDCB) to work on computational biology and machine learning approaches.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Congratulations Dr. Halima Hannah Schede!</title>
      <link>/post/halima_graduation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/halima_graduation/</guid>
      <description>We are delighted to announce that Halima Hannah Schede has successfully defended her PhD thesis!
Halima joined as a PhD student in 2020 and completed her thesis jointly supervised with Prof. D&amp;rsquo;Angelo. Her research focused on computational approaches for spatialomics data: construction, integration, and analysis of biomolecular atlases. She developed Tomographer and made key contributions to the Lipid Brain Atlas project.
Halima has accepted a position as Lead Data Scientist at Implexis Ltd in London.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Congratulations Dr. Alex Lederer!</title>
      <link>/post/alex_graduation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/alex_graduation/</guid>
      <description>We are thrilled to celebrate Alex Lederer&amp;rsquo;s successful PhD defense!
Alex joined the lab as a PhD student in the Computational and Quantitative Biology program (EDCB) in 2019. His research focused on deciphering the nature of cell state transitions in single cells using quantitative modeling of temporal dynamics. His work contributed to major advances in RNA velocity methods, including developments in VeloCycle.
Alex has now moved on to become a Senior Data Scientist at CHUV.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome Xinyi, Morgane, and Alireza!</title>
      <link>/post/2024_cohort_joins/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2024_cohort_joins/</guid>
      <description>We are excited to welcome three new PhD students to the La Manno Lab!
Xinyi Huang joins us from the Biotechnology and Bioengineering Program (EDBB) to work on brain development research.
Morgane Storey joins as a joint PhD student in the Neuroscience Program (EDNE) between our lab and Prof. Petersen&amp;rsquo;s lab, working on neuroscience and brain development.
Alireza Gargoorimothlag joins from the Neuroscience Program (EDNE) to develop computational approaches for understanding brain development using spatial transcriptomics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome Luca and Alessandro!</title>
      <link>/post/lucaale_join/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/lucaale_join/</guid>
      <description>Luca Fusar Bassini and Alessandro Valente join the lab for their PhD. Luca is a Biologist with a keen interest in developing computational methods to distill biological insight out of data, Alessandro is Biotechnologist with excellent experience in stem cell engineering and brain organoid models. They are both going to work on the lipidome-transcriptome axis in neurulation. Welcome Luca and Alessandro!.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome Dimitri!</title>
      <link>/post/dimitri_joins/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/dimitri_joins/</guid>
      <description>Dimitri Lallement joins the lab for a Masters thesis project. He is enrolled in the Computer Science Engineering program, ENSIMAG at Grenoble and doing a exchange with EPFL. He has studied his Bachelor at the University of Bordeaux and studied as Data Scientist Junior at CNES. He wants to face challenging research problem and explore new methods that can help the interpretation of single-cell RNAseq datasets. Welcome Dimitri!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome Halima!</title>
      <link>/post/halima_joins/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/halima_joins/</guid>
      <description>Halima Schede joins the lab for a Masters project. She is enrolled in the Bioengineering program and has studied in biology and mathematics at McGill. With her passion for machine learning and neural networks and her knowledge of anatomy and genetics she will turn a bunch of omics data in useful insights of the molecular anatomy of the brain. Welcome Halima!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome Anurag!</title>
      <link>/post/anurag_joins/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/anurag_joins/</guid>
      <description>Anurag Ranjak joins the lab for a Masters project. Anurag is a Chemical Engineer with industry experience in software engineering. He will adventure in spatial transcriptpomics and image reconstruction.He recently &amp;ldquo;converted&amp;rdquo; to biology and enrolled in EPFL Masters in Life Sciences. Welcome Anurag!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visiting EPFL and super-postdocs in Europe</title>
      <link>/post/elifrcandidate/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/elifrcandidate/</guid>
      <description>Over the last few days I have been at the École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne (EPFL), Switzerland. The reason of this little trip is that the School of Life Sciences at EPFL recently opened a special position, the fellowship goes under the long name &amp;ldquo;EPFL Life Sciences Early Independence Research Scholar&amp;rdquo; shortened &amp;ldquo;ELIFR fellow&amp;rdquo;.
To explain what an ELIFR fellow is I could simply refer to it as a &amp;ldquo;super-postdoc&amp;rdquo;, a funny term popularized by this commentary on Cell but maybe, not yet so popular in Europe (so that I noticed that using it in a conversation often produces raised eyebrows and a grin or two).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>