<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Gioele La Manno</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Gioele La Manno</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome Halima!</title>
      <link>/post/halima_joins/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/halima_joins/</guid>
      <description>Halima Schedek joins the lab for a Masters project. She is enrolled in the Bioengineering program and has studied in biology and mathematics at McGill. With her passion for machine learning and neural networks and her knowledge of anatomy and genetics she will turn a bunch of omics data in useful insights of the molecular anatomy of the brain. Welcome Halima!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome Anurag!</title>
      <link>/post/anurag_joins/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/anurag_joins/</guid>
      <description>Anurag Ranjak joins the lab for a Masters project. Anurag is a Chemical Engineer with industry experience in software engineering. He will adventure in spatial transcriptpomics and image reconstruction.He recently &amp;ldquo;converted&amp;rdquo; to biology and enrolled in EPFL Masters in Life Sciences. Welcome Anurag!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RNA velocity is out in Nature</title>
      <link>/post/velocitynature/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/velocitynature/</guid>
      <description>In a previous preprint RNA velocity in single cells we had presented the discovery that standard RNA-seq data contains additional information on the rate and direction of change in gene expression. If you haven&amp;rsquo;t read what this is about you can see my previous post or directly go and read the more eloquent Nature News and Views kindly written by Allon Klein.
Now our work has gone through the process of peer review.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visiting EPFL and super-postdocs in Europe</title>
      <link>/post/elifrcandidate/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 May 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/elifrcandidate/</guid>
      <description>Over the last few days I have been at the École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne (EPFL), Switzerland. The reason of this little trip is that the School of Life Sciences at EPFL recently opened a special position, the fellowship goes under the long name &amp;ldquo;EPFL Life Sciences Early Independence Research Scholar&amp;rdquo; shortened &amp;ldquo;ELIFR fellow&amp;rdquo;.
To explain what an ELIFR fellow is I could simply refer to it as a &amp;ldquo;super-postdoc&amp;rdquo;, a funny term popularized by this commentary on Cell but maybe, not yet so popular in Europe (so that I noticed that using it in a conversation often produces raised eyebrows and a grin or two).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>osmFISH is really awesome</title>
      <link>/post/osmfish/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/osmfish/</guid>
      <description>Simone Codelluppi and Lars Borm have developed and optimized a cyclic smFISH protocol, termed ouroboros smFISH, to quantify the expression of a large number of genes in tissue sections. The goal was building a cell type map of the mouse somatosensory cortex. The results are really impressive. See the fantastic images and interactively explore the data using the Loom viewer here.
Great news are not only is taht Lars and Simore have put a lot of effort to make it possible for any lab to set up the method and they provide detailed protocol and a polished software package.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RNA velocity preprint</title>
      <link>/post/velocity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/velocity/</guid>
      <description>Single-cell RNA-seq measurements provide a powerful approach for studying complex biological tissues. Some of the more interesting contexts involve dynamic processes, such as development or disease progression. However single-cell measurements only capture a snapshot of a transcriptional state at a single point in time.
Several approaches have been developed to infer dynamic processes, such as branching lineages from this scRNA-seq. Usually those methods require many strong assumptions that are often violated.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>