<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Group Leader on Gioele La Manno</title>
    <link>/tags/group-leader/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Group Leader on Gioele La Manno</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/group-leader/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Gioele La Manno</title>
      <link>/people/gioelelamanno/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/gioelelamanno/</guid>
      <description>Bio I earned my PhD at Karolinska Instituet and I am proud alumnus of the Linnarsson Lab. My original training is in Biotechnology (BSc @UNIPA) and Biomedicine (MSc @KI) but nowadays I will probably turn around if somebody is calling out for a Molecular Biologist, Computational Biologist or Bioinformatician.
My research focuses on understanding brain development. I am particularly interested in describing the sequence of states that embryonic stem cells go through during their differentiation towards mature neurons.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open Positions</title>
      <link>/people/openposition1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/openposition1/</guid>
      <description>Openings and available projects Postdoctoral researcher Read the full call in pdf here!
The research project offered will be focused on the spatio-temporal organization of neural progenitor cells across the developing nervous systems in health and disease. The project, funded by SNF, is low-risk and high-impact.
The overarching goal is understanding the functional implications of the distribution and abundance of radial glial subtypes and the modalities teratogens and metabolic alterations can disrupt it.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>