<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Group Leader on Gioele La Manno</title>
    <link>/tags/group-leader/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Group Leader on Gioele La Manno</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 18 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/group-leader/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Gioele La Manno</title>
      <link>/people/gioelelamanno/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/gioelelamanno/</guid>
      <description>Bio I earned my PhD at Karolinska Instituet and I am proud alumnus of the Linnarsson Lab. My original training is in Biotechnology (BSc @UNIPA) and Biomedicine (MSc @KI) but nowadays I will probably turn around if somebody is calling out for a Molecular Biologist, Computational Biologist or Bioinformatician.
My research focuses on understanding brain development. I am particularly interested in describing the sequence of states that embryonic stem cells go through during their differentiation towards mature neurons.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Open Positions</title>
      <link>/people/openposition1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/openposition1/</guid>
      <description>Openings and available projects Postdoctoral researcher We are looking for a talented individual interested in developmental biology, the nervous system and the retina. We particularly welcome applications from experimentalists with experience working with some of the following: mouse embryos, Crispr-Cas9 system, cloning, microscopy, FACS sorting, preparation of sequencing libraries.
PhD student position An interdisciplinary Ph.D. project in developmental neuroscience and systems biology is available at La Manno lab. The successful candidate will use a combination of cutting-edge single-cell genomics techniques, including RNA velocity, to study the embryonic development of the retina.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>