<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>PhD Student on Gioele La Manno</title>
    <link>/tags/phd-student/</link>
    <description>Recent content in PhD Student on Gioele La Manno</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/phd-student/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Christian Schneider</title>
      <link>/people/christianschneider/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/christianschneider/</guid>
      <description>Short Bio I am an MD student visiting EPFL as part of my doctoral research project. While studying medicine at Charité, my research focus has been developing molecular biotechnologies for clinical application in neurological diseases, with projects based in Berlin, India and Central Africa. As part of my home university’s lab for Translational Neurogenomics, I joined the La Manno Lab with a key interest in quantitative systems biology of single cells.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ece Asirim</title>
      <link>/people/eceasirim/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/eceasirim/</guid>
      <description>Short Bio I am a joint PhD student in the Neuroscience Program (EDNE) between the La Manno and D&amp;rsquo;Angelo Labs. I completed my MSc degree in University of Fribourg, working on Drosophila larval circadian rhythms. My current project focuses on lipidomics and neuroscience, as in the central nervous system, lipids play a crucial role by influencing the firing of neurons and synaptic plasticity. To address the lacking knowledge of lipid metabolism in different brain regions, we aim to build a high-resolution atlas of lipid metabolism in adult mouse brain, both in health and disease conditions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Irina Khven</title>
      <link>/people/irinakhven/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/irinakhven/</guid>
      <description>Short Bio I have recently completed my Masters at Moscow State University, Department of Bioengineering and Bioinformatics. During my undergraduate studies I’ve worked in a molecular biology lab and received a comprehensive training in many techniques. Both of my internships, one in the Weis lab at ETH Zurich and another in the Seigert lab at IST Austria, helped me realize that molecular neuroscience is the most exciting branch of modern biology to me.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alex Lederer</title>
      <link>/people/alexlederer/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/alexlederer/</guid>
      <description>Short Bio I am a PhD student in the Computational and Quantitative Biology (EDCB) program at EPFL. Originally from the United States, I completed my BSc in Molecular Biology and Computer Science at the University of Pittsburgh before working as a research fellow at EMBL Heidelberg.
During my studies, I have been captivated by the concept of temporal omics and bioinformatics in light of the big data boom and advances in next-generation sequencing technologies.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>