<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>PhD Student on Gioele La Manno</title>
    <link>/tags/phd-student/</link>
    <description>Recent content in PhD Student on Gioele La Manno</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/phd-student/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Lada Polyakova</title>
      <link>/people/ladapolyakova/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/ladapolyakova/</guid>
      <description>Blurb I am a PhD student in the Computational and Quantitative Biology Program (EDCB) at EPFL, working in the La Manno Lab.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Laura Lapeña Gil</title>
      <link>/people/lauralapena/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/lauralapena/</guid>
      <description>Blurb I am a PhD student in the Neuroscience Program (EDNE) at EPFL, working in the La Manno Lab.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alireza Gargoorimothlag</title>
      <link>/people/alirezagargoorimothlag/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/alirezagargoorimothlag/</guid>
      <description>Blurb I am a PhD student in the Computational Biology Program (EDCB) at EPFL, working in the La Manno Lab on the intersection of machine learning methods and single-cell/spatial omics for understanding brain development.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Morgane Storey</title>
      <link>/people/morganestorey/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/morganestorey/</guid>
      <description>Blurb I am a joint PhD student in the Neuroscience Program (EDNE) between the La Manno Lab and Prof. Petersen&amp;rsquo;s lab at EPFL.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Xinyi Huang</title>
      <link>/people/xinyihuang/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/xinyihuang/</guid>
      <description>Blurb I am a PhD student in the Biotechnology and Bioengineering Program (EDBB) at EPFL, working in the La Manno Lab.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Luca Fusar Bassini</title>
      <link>/people/lucafusar/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/lucafusar/</guid>
      <description>Blurb I am a PhD student in Computational Biology at EPFL under Prof. Gioele La Manno, focusing on multiomics and dynamic modeling in neurodevelopment to advance our understanding of neurodevelopmental disorders. My background includes quantitative training at Scuola Normale di Pisa and rare disease research at Boston Children&amp;rsquo;s Hospital. Passionate about the intersection of bio and AI, I also host podcasts, write for Wired Italia, and engage in science dissemination through LauzHack and Lead The Future.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alessandro Valente</title>
      <link>/people/alessandrovalente/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/alessandrovalente/</guid>
      <description>Blurb I am a PhD student in the Neuroscience Program (EDNE) in the La Manno Lab. I have a strong interest in the applications of statistical models and data analysis to the health sciences. After completing my M.Sc. in Biotechnology and Bioengineering at the University of Milan, during which I completed an internship in the La Manno Lab, I returned to the lab full time as a PhD student.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rosan Hans</title>
      <link>/people/rosanhans/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/rosanhans/</guid>
      <description>Blurb I am an Industrial PhD student in the Biotechnology and Bioengineering Program (EDBB) at EPFL, working jointly with the La Manno Lab and Roche IHB, supervised by Dr. Giuliana Rossi.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Albert Dominguez Mantes</title>
      <link>/people/albertmantes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/people/albertmantes/</guid>
      <description>Blurb I am a joint PhD student in the Computational and Quantitative Biology Program (EDCB) between the La Manno lab and the Weigert lab (TU Dresden, Germany). My main focus is on developing computer vision methods for the analysis of microscopy images. One of my main goals is on developing methods that are easily adoptable for other researchers. As such, I’m big on open source and best software engineering practices.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>