<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>publications on Gioele La Manno</title>
    <link>/tags/publications/</link>
    <description>Recent content in publications on Gioele La Manno</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/publications/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Lipid Brain Atlas preprint released</title>
      <link>/post/lipid_brain_atlas/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/lipid_brain_atlas/</guid>
      <description>We are excited to announce the release of our preprint &amp;ldquo;The Lipidomics Architecture of the Mouse Brain&amp;rdquo; on bioRxiv!
This work represents a major milestone for our lab, presenting the first comprehensive spatial lipidomic atlas of the adult mouse brain. Using high-resolution MALDI mass spectrometry imaging, we mapped 172 membrane lipids across 109 sections and 11 brains, all registered to the Allen Brain Atlas.
Key findings: - We identified 539 spatially coherent biochemical domains, which we call &amp;ldquo;lipizones&amp;rdquo; - Lipizones capture both neuronal cell bodies and their distal terminals - White matter shows marked regional heterogeneity driven by oligodendrocyte-specific lipids - We discovered that pregnancy induces coordinated lipid remodeling in the cortex and white matter</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>uMAIA published in Nature Methods</title>
      <link>/post/umaia_natmethods/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/umaia_natmethods/</guid>
      <description>We are excited to announce the publication of our work on uMAIA (unified Mass Imaging Analyzer) in Nature Methods.
uMAIA is an analytical framework for the joint analysis of large mass spectrometry imaging datasets. It enables the construction of multidimensional metabolomic atlases by extracting, aligning, and normalizing data into coherent, accurate maps. We applied this framework to study developmental lipidomics, creating detailed 4D lipid maps across embryonic stages.
This work represents a significant step forward in our understanding of how lipid diversity contributes to brain development and cellular identity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spotiflow published in Nature Methods</title>
      <link>/post/spotiflow_natmethods/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/spotiflow_natmethods/</guid>
      <description>We are pleased to announce the publication of Spotiflow in Nature Methods.
Spotiflow is a deep learning method for subpixel-accurate spot detection in fluorescence microscopy images. The method formulates spot detection as a multiscale heatmap and stereographic flow regression problem, achieving state-of-the-art performance on diverse datasets while being robust to different noise conditions.
Key features include: - Subpixel-accurate 2D and 3D spot detection - Optimized for spatial transcriptomics workflows - Robust to low signal-to-noise ratio images - Available as Python library and napari plugin</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>VeloCycle published in Nature Methods</title>
      <link>/post/velocycle_natmethods/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/velocycle_natmethods/</guid>
      <description>We are excited to announce the publication of VeloCycle in Nature Methods.
VeloCycle is a Bayesian model of RNA velocity that couples velocity field and manifold estimation in a unified framework, enabling formal statistical testing of gene expression dynamics. It fits an inferentially coherent model directly on raw data, eliminating heuristics that dominate current scRNA analyses.
Key features include: - Formal statistical testing of dynamics - End-to-end Bayesian inference - Cell cycle speed quantification - Manifold-constrained velocity estimation</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>